I've been uh sitting on this
investigation for over a year now, and
today is the day that we'll finally be
deep diving into the seed oil
controversy. And here's the catch. Even
if you're familiar with the anti-seed
oil argument, I'll bet you've never
heard some of the arguments that I'll be
presenting against seed oils right here,
right now. You see, while health
influencers lob claim after claim
without any scientific backing, there is
an actual group of researchers that also
believe seed oils, omega sixs, may be
harmful. And yet, I've never heard
anyone dive into their findings. So,
let's get into it. This is going to be
detailed. It's going to be long. So,
buckle in. If you aren't familiar with
what seed oils are, they're omega-6
polyunsaturated fats. And if you're
unfamiliar with what that is, they're a
particular type of fat like the ones
that you eat that have a molecular
structure that creates a kink. Actually,
multiple kinks in that structure. Now,
because of their structure, they are
more susceptible to damage from damaging
molecules like reactive oxygen species
and other free radicals that are formed
by your cells under circumstances like
when you smoke, when you're over fat,
come in contact with air pollutants, and
any number of other exposures. The point
being, these fats, these seed oils, are
more likely to be damaged, contributing
to hypothetically worse health. I'm sure
there are other arguments for their
negative health consequences, but we're
here to discuss the clinical data in
humans. If people consume more seed
oils, do they experience more health
issues? That's the big question.
Regardless of the mechanism, like I
promised, there are researchers that
argue that seed oils, these omega-6
fats, are detrimental. And there's this
back and forth debate between this group
and another group that disagree. These
researchers put together multiple
randomized control trials up to the
point of that analysis's release looking
at seed oil or omega-6 fat consuming
groups compared against nonseed oil
consuming groups. So this analysis
included seven studies and we can see
them here. We have the studies on the
left side. The MCS study there is broken
up into two groups split by sex and we
have the results on the right. Okay. If
you've never seen this before, there's a
one line in the middle, which indicates
no increased or reduced risk from
consuming omega sixes. If the squares
and the lines move to the right, that
indicates increased risk, and the
opposite if it moves to the left. The
overall effect, all the studies
included, is the diamond. Oddly, there's
three diamonds. And that's because the
researchers have an overall diamond
including all the studies on the very
bottom. And then they have split the
studies if the study included omega sixs
only or if they're given omega sixs plus
omega-3s. Each getting their own diamond
and telling a different story. This is
where the first mystery begins. If we
focus on the overall effects diamond,
it's squarely in the middle indicating
no increased mortality risk. But if we
look at the top grouping, the studies
including omega-3s, the diamond leans to
the left, indicating potentially reduced
harm. On the other hand, the bottom
grouping leans to the right, indicating
potential increased harm. The combined
effects leads to this neutral effect.
Yet, both subgroups with or without
omega-3s are not statistically
significant. So, why do these
researchers think that omega sixs are
harmful then? Well, it comes down to the
split between omega-3 inclusion. They
mentioned that other studies have been
confounded, muddied by the fact that
participants not only consumed more
omega sixs, but also consumed omega-3s.
Omega-3s are also polyunsaturated fats,
but their chemical structure is slightly
different and have been linked to
positive health outcomes. Think like
algae oil, fish oil, krill oil, salmon,
and so on. Yet, according to them, if
you only focus on the studies using
omega6 alone, we can start to see this
divergent effect. No longer is the data
trending toward benefit. In fact, if we
look at some of their other data, that
trend becomes more clear. In these data,
it's the same idea, but instead of all-c
causeed mortality, we're looking at
coronary heart disease. Here we clearly
see that the addition of omega-3s
improves coronary heart disease as it
clearly shifts to the left of the one
line. But again, we don't see that when
just looking at omega sixes, the seed
oils. Unfortunately, the researchers
only had three groups of people instead
of four like in the all-c cause
mortality data because the Sydney trial
only looked at all- cause mortality.
They argue that if they'd had the data
from the Sydney trial, they'd detect an
increase in coronary heart disease. But
wishes and hopes aren't going to
convince us science-minded individuals,
right? Fortunately, these researchers
didn't stop there, and they actually got
their hands on the data. But before we
get to their updated analysis, which is
quite revealing, let me introduce you to
the disagreeing party, the pro-se
research group. This group wrote a
response to this analysis that we just
went over. Therein they seem to almost
gaslight the first group that we just
went over. I can't believe I use the
word gaslight, but here we are. They
literally right
at all have recently confirmed that many
other studies have shown the consumption
of vegetable oils rich in omega-6
polyunsaturated fats lowers risk of
coronary heart disease.
Uh, excuse me. Did they read the same
analysis that we just did? They also
push back on the omega sixes alone
potentially increasing coronary heart
disease because there's limited studies
and the results were not statistically
significant. I think that's a fair point
because it's technically true. Still,
the lack of an effect when an analysis
doesn't have enough data doesn't mean
that there isn't an effect there to be
detected. They also point out that other
studies, especially highly controlled
metabolic wart studies where everything
is given and controlled by the
researchers, indicate improved blood
markers from consuming omega6es. This is
also shown in epidemiological studies.
We'll come back to that point in a
little bit. So Ramsden, the first
research group, collapsed back in their
own letter by saying, "Harisol
apparently overlooked the central
finding of our analysis that omega 6 and
omega 3 plus omega 6 interventions have
significantly different effects on
risk." Okay, Ramse, I see you.
They also continue to point out that the
argument by Harris at all is
inaccurately portrayed as they fail to
mention the Sydney heart trial in the
all-C cause mortality data and the fact
that most of the participants in that
trial died from coronary heart disease.
Admittedly, I found this rebuttal far
better because it's true that the main
point of the Ramston analysis was that
seed oils alone create different effects
than seed oils plus omega-3s. But
there's this lingering problem that were
speculating on the Sydney heart trial
since we don't have that data or at
least we didn't then. Fast forward a few
years and guess what happens? The
Ramston group analyzes the Sydney heart
trial data for coronary heart disease
and cardiovascular death here. Now if we
look at the results of their analysis,
we can see the Sydney heart trial or the
Sydney diet heart study has now been
added. And lo and behold, the diamond
squarely shifts strongly to the right,
indicating a greater coronary heart
disease deaths from only consuming more
omega-6 fats. Now to be transparent, the
p value was 0.06. So technically not
statistically significant, although
extremely close. So now we have even
more evidence that seed oils cause
death. The same was true for
cardiovascular death as a whole,
assuming that we accept this 0.06 p
value. Wow. Okay. So, I love the nuance
of splitting omega sixs from omega-3s
because it's true that could be a major
factor in how we interpret these data. I
also love that they're using randomized
control trials which are powerful tools
of evidence.
But, ah, yes, the ass that turneth
tails, but there's so much more to this
story. Do we need an intermission?
Maybe, I don't know, grab some snacks.
The tricky thing is, should they be seed
oilbased or not? So far, no. But is this
story about to take a turn? Well, we've
discussed one perspective, and it's
clearly full of potent material. But
there's another perspective to be had
here. So, let's have at it. More recent
meta analyses have also pulled together
randomized control trials, including
more recent ones. For example, in this
analysis, the researcher actually only
included the same older studies from the
60s up to the 80s. From our initial
analysis, we can see that the from the
data here that we're looking at the same
coronary heart disease deaths. You can
see that the researcher has split
studies by if they're adequately
controlled or not. Meaning if the
studies had higher risk of major
confounding like I don't know employing
multiple changes other than just
increasing omega sixs or the studies
weren't randomized and any number of
other potential biasing factors. As we
can see in the studies that fit as
higher risk of bias omega sixs reduce
risk of coronary heart disease death.
But when we focus on the better
controlled studies that benefit is lost.
Obviously, it seems nonsensical to go by
the poorly controlled studies, but even
the better studies indicate no harm
either. If we shift to this uh third
analysis, it includes 19 studies ranging
from the 60s up to the 2000s with more
data. Do we see a change in the results?
Well, this analysis has a ton of data
with many, many comparisons that we
won't be able to get into here. So, I'm
going to highlight some and uh leave
more, including cancer outcomes if
multiple factors like weight, age, and
more make a difference for the extended
version of this video that you're
watching. Believe it or not, there's
much more to discuss that I can't fit in
here. You can access the full analysis
along with all my other analyses, live
sessions with me, a private podcast,
shortened summaries with applicable
takeaways on your health, and much more
in the Physionic Insider community. You
can access all of that through the link
in the description. I'd love for you to
join. So in this Cochran analysis, if we
consider all cause mortality first, we
can see the overall result is no effect
one way or another, not favoring more or
less omega sixs. If we specifically look
at the cardiovascular mortality, we also
see similar lack of an effect regardless
of the statistical test used. So what do
we make of all this? We have some
analyses saying there's a negative
effect, some indicating positive but
unreliably, and most showing no effect.
Well, I can answer that based on what we
have because there's a few key pieces of
information that I've left out so far
that will be quite illuminating. But
before we shine light on those, let's
pour another 150 studies into this
analysis using this global meta
analysis.
We're straying from our randomized
control trials and looking at much
longer, much bigger prospective
observational studies. These studies
have far greater difficulty identifying
cause than control trials. But they
offer certain advantages like having
much greater pools of data from hundreds
of thousands of participants and over
several decades instead of a few hundred
participants over two or three years. So
looking at these data and focusing in on
all-c cause mortality again we have the
study names on the left. You'll notice
the different size squares that
identifies how much weight or impact
that study has on the analysis. We have
our trusty one line. And this time if
the squares and the overall diamond move
to the left that indicates reduced
mortality risk with greater omega-6
consumption which is what we see here.
Okay. A few nuances to be applied here.
First, because this is an analysis of
associative studies, a statistical test
has to be applied to the data to account
for potential other factors causing the
effect. For example, if people lose
weight and they're consuming more seed
oils, it's possible that the weight loss
is the real reason that they experience
reduced mortality risk. As such, the
researchers employ what's known as a
multivaried analysis where they account
for multiple factors. Here's a list.
Unfortunately, because this is such a
big analysis, they're not reanalyzing
the original data from all 150 studies.
And some studies applied all these
adjustments and others only applied some
of them. So, we can't say that the
analysis is universally adjusted for
these common influencing factors. This
is a potential weakness of the study and
even the researchers acknowledge that.
On the other hand, this analysis does
something no other analysis does. It
also looks at studies measuring
circulating omega sixes, not just the
consumed omega6. All the control trials
that we looked at earlier were measuring
dietary omega6. But many of these
studies are measuring blood and cell
integrated omega sixs, which is a better
marker of the length of exposure and the
amount of real exposure than dietary
intake. This is a big plus. In the end,
this analysis with its strengths and
weaknesses beyond the scope of this
content indicates increasing omega sixes
is associated with better outcomes. Now,
if you'll allow me to bring in one more
player into this story, we'll discuss it
and then I'd like to return to the
beginning before we package this all up
into some actionable takeaways. Remember
how we discussed the omega-3s being a
factor? the fats that have been linked
to positive health outcomes, the ones
found in fish, as one example. There are
studies comparing circulating omega sixs
relative to omega-3s, and they found
some fascinating results. If we look at
the mortality risk again on the vertical
axis there, and we use a reference of
omega 6 to omega 3 in the blood, we can
assess the risk of mortality relative to
that reference. The reference was set to
four. So four units of omega 6 for every
1 unit of omega 3. You can see the
reference on the horizontal axis. As
omega 3 is reduced or omega 6 is
increased the ratio increases. If the
red line moves up that indicates
increased risk. If it goes down from the
trusty dotted one line running
horizontally that indicates reduced
risk. Now I don't need to spell it out.
You can see that if the ratio increases
either more omega-6 or less omega-3,
there's an increased mortality risk.
Okay, so this might fall in line with
the initial Ramston analysis that we
discussed, right? If you diminish
omega-3 or over consume omega6, you'll
see this poor health relationship.
Here's the thing, though. We need to
know how much the average person is
exposed to. And according to these
researchers and across 85,000 people,
the answer is a ratio of around nine.
Now using that nine, if we look back at
the graph, that nine is smack dab at the
point of reduced risk. However, the real
interpretation is no association with
risk. Risk only truly increased uh when
readings got around 14 or 15 ratio. Why
does this matter? Well, it points to
day-to-day consumption not leading to
dangerous levels of exposure. I should
mention three things about this analysis
too. One, it is associative across 13
years, but unlike the previous analysis,
the researchers were able to use all the
raw data to perform uniform statistic
adjustment for the confounders here.
Secondly, other studies estimate higher
omega-6 exposure closer at around 15,
right around where risk might increase.
However, those older analyses generally
use consumption data and assume
exposure. This analysis used a sensitive
measure looking directly at the blood
values, not consumption. So, this
measure is likely more accurate. And
thirdly, the researchers specifically
point out that they did not believe that
this link is due to increased omega-6,
but rather insufficient omega-3. There's
more to be said about this particular
study, but I'll leave that for the full
analysis. See the Physionic Insiders if
you're interested, link in the
description. Okay, let's begin bringing
this ship home by revisiting our very
first debate, this analysis. Okay,
remember this? This was the all cause
mortality data. I'd like to take a more
detailed look at these three studies.
Don't worry, I'm not going to go on
another three study breakdown except to
mention a few things you likely wouldn't
know about these studies. The Sydney
Hark trial that we discussed earlier did
show an increase in mortality in the
omega-6 consuming group. But what's not
mentioned is the fact that multiple
researchers have pointed out that the
Sydney trial replaced saturated fats
with margarine that contained trans
fats. Those are the fats that are now
banned because they're of their extreme
harm to health. At the time in the
late60s, scientists didn't know that
trans fats were especially harmful. So
to be clear, this group of researchers
have said that they don't believe that
omega6 group consumed more trans fats,
but there's good evidence that they did.
I have a separate analysis on this study
alone if you're interested in more
details on that. So is it then fair to
compare omega6, including trans fats,
against lower omega6 and lower trans
fats? Probably not. There are some other
issues with that trial, but I'll leave
those critiques for my dedicated
analysis. Next is the rose corn oil
trial. The omega-6 group consumed corn
oil every day for about 2 years. What
this Ramston analysis fails to mention
is that the participants also consumed
700 more calories per day than the
control group. So, do you consider it
fair to compare a lower omega6 lower
calorie diet against a higher omega6
higher calorie diet and then blame omega
sixs as the sole cause? This is a
massive confounding variable. Not to
mention, the study included 54 people.
Some people didn't comply with the study
and more. By the way, these were uh
things discussed explicitly and
adequately accounted for in this later
analysis. Now, the grand prize, the MCS
or Minnesota coronary survey. This one
is a doozy because while yes, it's also
possible the seed oil omega6 group
consumed more trans fats, that isn't the
biggest critique of that study. What if
I told you over 70% of the participants
dropped out of the study because they
were released from the institution that
they were being held in? Trying to
publish a study where you lose over 70%
of your participants in the first year
would be wild. But the data was
recovered and published anyway. Yet,
while this Ramsden analysis mentions the
positives of the Minnesota coronary
survey, like indicating specific
cardiovascular risk to women, they fail
to mention that uh tiny matter of losing
most of the participants. But it gets
better. There is a study called the
Finnish Mental Hospital Study or FMS and
it was excluded from this analysis
because, and get this, the participants
were fed trans fats. and the study
design was poor. Now, to be fair, those
are good critiques and good reasons for
exclusion if you choose. But those same
exact critiques could be levied against
at least the Minnesota Coronary Survey.
Not to mention, the FMHS study found the
omega6 consuming group experienced
significant cardiovascular
protection. So, we include a bad study
indicating harm of omega sixs, but we
exclude a bad study showing the benefit
of omega sixes.
Where's the consistency? Again, to be
fair, some of the included trials on
omega3 plus omega6 also had
methodological flaws, big ones, like the
Oslo study, which included multiple
interventions, not just omega-3 and
omega6 fats. The overall point being
here is that this meta analysis is
extremely inconsistent and includes
studies of at the very least low quality
while also not acknowledging these
massive confounding variables. So if we
remove all the trials that have
significant issues, the Sydney heart
trial, the Rose Corn Oil trial, the
Minnesota Coronary Survey, and we still
are keeping the uh Finnish mental
hospital study out, and even the Oslo
trial, we're left with a skeleton of an
analysis, and the backbone of this anti-
Omega6 argument gets crushed.
Still, does that actually mean that
omega 6s are not a risk? Just because
this analysis was poor doesn't
automatically mean that seed oils are
beneficial. Well, since most studies on
seed oils are from the 50s,60s,7s, and
80s, we don't have much data on the
current day to look at newer randomized
control trials. Yet, if we rely on other
types of studies like the few that we
went over, including what few relatively
well-controlled randomized control
trials remain, the evidence points more
strongly in the direction that omega6
fats have a neutral or beneficial effect
in regard to cardiovascular disease and
overall mortality. It is possible that
too much of these omega sixs could lead
to problems. I don't think that we have
a clear idea of that, but here are a few
actionable things to keep in mind. One,
unless you're downing vegetable oil on a
daily basis, your omega-6 levels are
likely in the range of neutral or no
risk, at least even with regular
consumption of other foods that may be
exposed to vegetable oils. In addition,
most researchers seem more worried about
under consuming omega-3 than over
consuming omega6. Two, if you're
actually still concerned, consider
upping your omega-3 consumption to keep
your ratio of omega 6 to omega 3 in that
normal range around 4 to 8 or 9 ratio,
let's say. Even this is still an area of
debate, but you probably will be better
off for it regardless. Three, consider
that if you avoid seed oils, omega
sixes, what are you replacing those
with? other nutrients like certain
saturated fats may be more harmful. So
while the amount may still be something
to leave for future investigations and
more randomized control trials
considering the massive shortcomings of
the much older studies are needed. I
wouldn't avoid omega sixes altogether as
the available evidence suggests at least
some omega6 consumption tracks with
better health outcomes. Anyway, plenty
more to get into, but if you want to
know more about these studies, check out
this video. Thanks for hanging out with
me and I'll see you over